Now let's get started.
And today we will be finishing
up model-based reinforcement
learning, specifically a
way to use a learned model
with synthetic data
generation and when
to use model-based
reinforcement learning.
And then we're going to
be talking about multitask
imitation learning
and reinforcement
learning, including ways
to conditions on tasks,
different tasks as
goal-reaching tasks,
and an approach called
hindsight relabeling,
which you'll be implementing.
Cool.
So let's get back to model-based
reinforcement learning.
So last time, we
talked about a scenario
where we learned some model.
That model could be a
deterministic model.
It could also be modeling a
distribution over next states.
And in particular, you
could think about it
as trying to approximate
the distribution
over the next state, given
the current state and action.
And you can use this
model to actually predict
what will happen in the future.
And for example, if you have
an action that you think
you might take or
multiple actions
you think you
might take, you can
use this estimated distribution
to generate or imagine
what might happen
in the future if you
were to take those actions.
We talked about an
approach to behavior
that's quite different
from learning a policy,
where we're not actually
explicitly learning
a mapping from states to
actions and instead, on the fly,
we are thinking through,
for a given state,
what actions we should take.
And we called this planning.
And we talked about how
this sort of planning
can be done with gradient-based
or sampling-based optimization
over the next future horizon.
Then we also talked
about how it's
important to update the model
using the data collected
because then you'll be
able to actually learn
a better model in the realms
that you want to use that model.
And then periodically,
we also talked
about how you can replan to
help account for mistakes,
account for errors in
the model, and also react
to changes in the environment.
Cool.
The pros of this sort
of planning approach
is that it's simple.
It's easy to plug in
different goals or rewards
if you have a general
enough model, possibly
even at test time.
And the downside is that it's
compute intensive at test time.
It requires a lot of test time
compute at inference time.
And this particular
instantiation
was only practical for
short-horizon problems
or for very shaped rewards,
where you can plan over
some shorter horizon
rather than considering
an extremely long horizon.
And there's two reasons
why this is only
applicable to short horizons.
One is that as you
increase the horizon,
it becomes even more
compute intensive.
And the second reason is that
the model is not very accurate
when you try to apply it
multiple times to generate
a long trajectory.
Cool.
Now, there's a second
way that you can use
these kinds of learned models.
And that is to learn a policy.
And so that's what we'll
talk about right now.
And the key idea is
that we can actually
use this model of the future,
this kind of learned simulator,
to augment any sort of
data that we've collected.
So say that in the real world
or the real environment,
we've collected some data.
So we have some trajectories.
Some of this data could also
have been provided to us
in an offline data set.
And so maybe the data that we
have in the real environment
looks something like this.
Does anyone have
thoughts on ways
in which we might want to use
our learned model to augment
this data set right here?
Like, procedurally,
what would we
do to try to generate
synthetic data?
Yeah.
So the thought there was
that you could take--
you said you could
take the last state
and then generate
more from there.
So you could add on to
the last state here.
So that's one
thing you could do.
Other thoughts on
things you could do?
Yeah?
So something like dagger, where
you take the first part that's
run by the policy and then
the second part that's
from the model.
So it's kind of
similar to this, maybe.
But maybe you do it earlier.
Is that what you're saying?
Yeah.
So you don't just have
to start at the end.
You can also start anywhere
in the middle as well.
So you could, for example,
generate trajectories
from, really, any sort
of state in your buffer,
in your data set.
And then if you were to
do something like that,
then you would be
able to generate
data that looks like this,
where everything that is in red
is synthetic data or data that
was imagined using your model.
And then everything in
black is the real data
from the environment.
Now, one thing that
we talked about before
is that our model is
not very good to be--
like, you can't really
trust it if you were
to make a really long rollout.
And so one thing that
you can do is keep
these trajectories very short.
And so instead of having
these be almost as
long as your original
trajectories,
you could actually change them
to be just little short rollouts
that look something like
this and that basically
add a little bit more
coverage around the trajectory
in your data.
And so that would look
something like this.
And something like this
picture is often more
like what people
find works really
well in practice because of
inaccuracies in your model.
And so specifically--
say we have some example,
real trajectory.
Then maybe the first
way that you could
think about creating data--
maybe it wasn't the first way
that you guys thought about it.
But one simple
thing you could do
is just start from
initial states
and generate full
trajectories as if it
were the real environment.
But the downside there
is that the model may not
be accurate for long horizons.
And so you won't be able to
actually get very good state
coverage if you only start at
the initial state distribution
and don't actually end,
because you only want
to use fairly short rollouts.
You can also generate
partial trajectories
from the initial states.
But this won't give you good
coverage of the later states.
And so one thing that gets
the best of both worlds-- it
gets you good coverage
and also allows
you to use short
trajectories-- is
to generate these
partial trajectories
from all of the states
in your real data set.
So then what the full
algorithm looks like is,
you will first
collect real data.
We can call this Denv, before.
And then we will want to update
our model using the real data
so that our model is as
accurate as it can be.
And then we can generate data.
And the way this generation
process will look like
is first sample some
S from your real data.
And then generate a short
trajectory starting from S,
where you will roll out your
policy or whatever exploration
policy you have,
starting from S.
But then we'll be
doing this rollout
inside your learned model.
And so this will be
inside the world that
is instantiated from your
learned model and not
in the real environment.
This data will go into
some other data set.
Maybe we can call it Dgen
for D-generated data.
And then at the
end, you can simply
update your policy
using both the real data
and the generated data.
So update pi theta using
Denv and D generated.
And then repeat this process.
Whoops.
I misspelled real.
So the question
is, if you're only
generating short trajectories,
does that take longer
to converge to some goal?
So you can think of it
as kind of supplementing
the data that you have so far.
And when you start from states
that are closer to the goal
from when you
generate data there,
then you'll be close
to getting rewards.
And you'll be able to update.
When you're further,
this doesn't mean that--
this data won't
necessarily reach the goal.
But with reinforcement
learning algorithms,
you'll be able to
understand-- some of this data
might feed into states
that are in the data.
And when you use
reinforcement learning,
you can then learn that--
like, as an example, maybe
you have a real trajectory
that takes a path that is
maybe not the most direct path.
And then you start learning
a policy that knows,
maybe I should shortcut this.
Then your model,
when you explore
that in your
synthetic data, this
might actually help you
learn a better policy
by using this kind of data.
In terms of convergence
speed or speed
in which you'll
get a good policy,
generally, the thing that
we're often trying to minimize
is the amount of real data
that we need right here.
And this will allow you to get a
good policy with less real data
by using these red trajectories.
Yeah.
So the question is, how do
we get rewards in this case?
So I haven't
explicitly written it
out here because
sometimes you might
know the form of
the reward function.
Or you might have
learned a reward function
in the original RL problem, in
which case you can use that.
If you didn't learn
a reward function
and the real world
just gives you
the rewards as
part of this data,
then when you train
this model, you'll
need for either this
model or a separate model
to also learn a reward function
with supervised learning.
So the question
was about compute.
So this is going to be
more compute intensive
during training than if you
were to not use this, especially
because sometimes the models
that you might be learning--
in some cases, the models
that you're learning,
usually rolling out through
them, takes compute.
You're kind of trading data in
the environment for compute.
And one of the reasons why that
trade-off is often favorable
is because collecting online
data in the real environment
might be unsafe,
or it might just
be really expensive if you
have to run experiments
on physical equipment.
Unlike planning, however, this
is not more compute intensive
at test time.
Because you're using
the synthetic data
to update a policy.
And then at test time,
you're running that policy
as your final behavior.
Cool.
So the algorithm on the
slides, we collect data.
We update our model.
This model may
also model rewards
by trying to mimic the
data from the environment.
Then we will collect these short
rollouts by using our model,
starting from states
in the real data.
And then we'll update the
policy and, optionally,
also update any sort
of value function using
the aggregated data.
One other thing
to note about this
is that it is compatible with
a variety of reinforcement
learning algorithms.
So step 4, you can use a
variety of algorithms here.
You can even use
on-policy reinforcement
learning algorithms as well.
In particular, if you have
an on-policy algorithm that
needs data from
the exact pi theta
that you're taking
a gradient step on,
all that means is
that pi theta has
to be the policy that was
collecting the synthetic data
through the model.
Cool.
Yeah.
So with regard to this
last update, here,
we're using both the data from
the environment and the data
from the model.
There are actually also
some policy updates
that only use data
from the model
and find that that
works fine as well.
So you can choose
to use either both
or just use the
data from the model.
Yeah.
So this only makes sense
when you have an estimate
of the reward function.
And if you don't,
then you won't be
able to update your policy
on the generated data.
So the question-- is
the learning stable
when you use the synthetic data?
Yeah, yeah.
So you may be in a
scenario where you're
adding a lot of synthetic data.
And so how much synthetic
data you generate
and how you balance that
data in this last update
might depend on how good
you think your model is.
In terms of stability,
I think that--
we'll talk about pros and
cons on the next slide.
But one downside of
these kinds of algorithms
is, they do introduce additional
hyperparameters because you
have to train this model.
And if, for example, your model
training, for whatever reason,
it didn't do well, then you
might end up in a scenario
where the algorithm
performs more
poorly because those
hyperparameters weren't
well tuned.
And so you can see issues there.
But otherwise, if you have
a fairly accurate model,
you usually don't have issues
otherwise with stability.
So let's talk a
little bit about when
to use this sort
of synthetic data
and when to use model-based
reinforcement learning.
So generally, the
way to think about it
is that there's
potentially really big
upsides with model-based
reinforcement learning
and also potentially
big downsides.
The big upside is that if you
can learn a pretty good model,
then it is immensely useful to
be able to predict the future.
And you can get away with
using far, far less real data
by using the data
that's generated.
And so in domains where it's
feasible to learn a model,
it's really, really useful.
You could also do the kind of
test time planning as well.
And generally, maybe
one other point
that's not on the slides
with regard to upsides
is that it seems like
this notion of being
able to anticipate future states
as an outcome of your actions,
that seems like a
fairly fundamental thing
that our models should at least
have some understanding for.
One other thing that we
actually didn't talk about
is, there are also scenarios
where the model can be
trained without reward labels.
And, for example, if some of
your real data has rewards
and some of it
doesn't have rewards,
the part that
you can train your model on.
And your model can actually
leverage potentially more data
than what a model-free
reinforcement learning
method can use.
And so that's quite nice.
And there are
scenarios where you
might be able to collect
very large amounts of data
without rewards and a small
amount of data with rewards.
And then the other thing is
that the model is somewhat
task agnostic.
And so if it was trained on a
broad enough data distribution,
sometimes you can transfer this
model across different tasks
or across different rewards.
And so, for example,
if your goal isn't just
to learn one task but to
learn many different tasks,
this sort of
transferability is useful.
So those are the big upsides.
What about the big downsides?
One downside is that the model
doesn't optimize for task
performance and errors.
Because it's trying
to-- for example,
if you have image observations
or your states are images,
then it's trying to get the
details in the pixels to line up
and that, for example, the color
of the sky is the correct color.
And that, in some
ways, oftentimes
is not actually what
you care about in terms
of learning a good policy.
So there's this
mismatch between what
you're optimizing for
when you train a model
and what you actually
might care about,
in terms of downstream
policy performance.
Sometimes it's really hard
to learn a good model.
Sometimes it's harder
to learn a good model
than it is to learn
a good policy.
In these cases,
usually, you don't
want to learn models because
you're then presenting a harder
problem than the actual
downstream problem you
might care about.
And then the last
thing that I alluded
to before is that it's another
thing you have to train.
And so there's more
hyperparameters,
and it's also more
compute intensive.
And so because of these
big upsides and downsides,
generally, whether
to try to learn
this kind of predictive model
depends a lot on the domain
and how hard it is to
learn that kind of model.
Yeah.
So the question was,
what are a few examples
of the additional
hyperparameters?
The main thing all comes down
to this step 2 right here,
which is that you need to design
the architecture of the model,
of this predictive model.
And it might need to be
a completely different
architecture from
the policy if you're
going to be generating
images or states.
The second is that you
need a learning rate.
You need to know how
long to train that for,
like how many epochs, any
regularization for that model,
basically everything that
might go into training
a model like this.
One more thing on that
previous question--
beyond training
this model, there's
also hyperparameters with regard
to the length of these rollouts
and how much synthetic
data to generate.
So the question is, do we
keep on collecting data
after each policy update?
So as written, this is
an online algorithm.
You can actually also develop
completely offline versions,
model-based RL
versions as well, where
you have a fixed prior
data set and you augment
that data set with a model.
And then you train a
policy, and you're done.
In this case, we have
an online algorithm,
where we then continue
to collect real data,
update our model, and so forth.
This can be done in
an off-policy way
or an on-policy way.
So that's going to come down
to, when you do this update,
is it going to only use the Denv
and the Dgen from this iteration
or also from
previous iterations?
And that's going to
depend on what algorithm
you use to update your policy.
So generally, models
are very flexible.
You can use them
offline, on policy,
off policy, and so forth.
Yeah.
So the question
is, how hard is it
to learn a model
compared to a policy?
It's extremely domain dependent.
So for example, say
you're in a maze.
So you're trying to learn
how to get from here to here.
Maybe there's some walls.
And you need to
figure out how to get
through this sort
of environment.
And you're not able to
go through the walls.
In this case, the model
might be quite easy to learn.
You'll learn that if your
action is to go right,
then you'll go right,
unless there's a wall there.
If you're going to go up and
so forth-- that's really easy.
But the policy is
really complicated.
Because the policy is saying
that, OK, if you're here,
maybe you need to go in
various different directions.
And so this is a case where the
policy is a lot more complicated
than the model.
And learning a model
could be a good choice.
As another example,
say that you're
trying to pour some
water from one cup
into a bowl or
something like that.
The policy might be
potentially fairly simple.
Like, maybe you're already even
holding the cup in your hand.
Then the policy might
be as simple as just
rotating your wrist.
But the model in
this sort of case
might involve the fluid dynamics
of how the water will pour
and what will happen,
for example, if it hits
the edge of the bowl or
the center of the bowl
or something like that.
And this is a scenario where the
model is a lot more complicated
than the policy.
And it's possible
that in this scenario,
it might be a lot easier
to just learn the policy
without learning the model.
So it really depends
on the domain.
Yeah.
So the question is, how
successful has model-based RL
been in robotics scenarios?
If you're dealing with
high-dimensional image
observations, it's arguably
been less successful.
If you have a more
compact state space,
like the positions of joints
and positions of objects,
then it's been a
lot more successful.
And with legged
robots, for example,
you can use model-based
RL pretty successfully
if you're mostly just trying
to learn, like, a blind walking
policy.
Or we saw the dexterous--
like, the hand manipulation,
where you knew the
position of the two balls.
It was also very
successful for that.
And I haven't tried to do
model-free RL for that problem.
Or even imitation learning
would be very, very challenging.
And so it's been extremely
successful there.
In scenarios where you need
to have image observations,
it gets a lot harder.
It doesn't mean that--
video-generative models
are getting a lot better.
And so I could see a future
where this sort of approach
might also be quite
successful in the future.
But right now, it hasn't
been super successful.
The last thing I'll
mention on model-based RL
is that so far, we've been
modeling this predictive model
of the future.
And there's actually
a lot of other objects
that you could learn.
So you could learn what's
called an inverse model.
You could learn,
for two states--
like, if I'm
currently in state st,
what is the action that would
lead to state st plus 1?
You could learn a
multistep inverse model,
which is, if I'm going to
end up at state st plus n,
what action would lead me there?
Or what are the
sequence of actions
that would lead me there?
Both of these, in some ways,
look closer to a policy,
except you're passing as input
some future state rather than
just the current state.
These are also things
that can be learned
without data with rewards.
You're kind of just learning
about the environment and not
about the particular
task at hand.
You can predict futures
without actions.
And that can think about,
what are the affordances
in my environment?
What are the things
that could be
possible to happen
in the future,
irrespective of the
actions that I take?
You could try to interpolate
between two states.
You could learn a generative
model of transitions of st
at st plus 1.
There's some cool properties
with that sort of model.
And these kind of models
can be pretty useful too.
They have various purposes.
There's lots of research on
using different kinds of models
like these.
And so it's just
something to think
about in terms of in some
domains you could imagine.
Or with some data sources,
you could imagine scenarios
where these might be useful.
Yeah.
So the question
is, if you use data
that doesn't have rewards as
part of your model training,
is there going to be a
mismatch between the accuracy
of predicting next states
and predicting rewards?
There certainly could
be a mismatch like that.
Generally, rewards are
a bit easier to learn
how to predict
than future states.
And so even if you
have a lot more data
for learning the model,
you could actually
end up in a scenario
where the model
is less accurate than
the estimated reward.
But yeah, you can definitely
end up with scenarios
where the reward
is less accurate
and where you need to
specifically gather
data for that.
Yeah.
Cool.
OK.
So that's it for model-based RL.
Now we're going to talk a
bit about multitask learning
and what that looks like and
also different techniques
that we can do, beyond a fairly
naive and simple technique.
So what is multitask
reinforcement learning?
The key idea is that we want to
be able to learn a generalist
policy that isn't just
aiming to do one thing,
like being able to pour
water, for example,
but that can do many
different things.
The examples of this--
we might want a generalist
language model assistant
that can book
travel for us, that
can do online grocery shopping.
We might want a legged robot
that can walk, that can run,
that can dance, that can crouch,
maybe a mobile robot that
can hang up a towel, unload
a dishwasher, wipe a spill,
maybe want a music recommender
system that can personalize
recommendations for
one person and also
be able to personalize
recommendations
to a different person.
Or we might want
something that can
play lots of different
games, like being
able to play Pokemon and pinball
and Flappy Bird and so forth.
And there are
scenarios where if you
think about each of these tasks
as their own reinforcement
learning problem, they
might have different reward
functions from other tasks.
They might, in some cases,
have different dynamics,
like the dynamics
of different games
or the dynamics of
different people.
They might have different
action spaces, even.
And so when you're
trying to train policies
across these different
tasks, there's
some considerations that come
up when you try to do that.
Now, the key idea that we'll see
is that you can, in many cases,
just go about
normal reinforcement
learning but
condition on the task
that you're trying to learn.
So you're then going to be
learning a policy that is not
just conditioned on
the state, but It's
conditioned on the
state and also the task
that you want it to be
performing for that state.
Now, why do we care about
multitask reinforcement
learning?
So if we go back to
a lot of the topics
that we've talked
about in the course
so far, like imitation learning,
on-policy and off-policy RL,
offline RL, model-based
RL, reward functions,
a big topic that's recurred
in many of these lectures
is talking about
data efficiency.
Like, how much data do we
need to be able to calculate
a gradient that is accurate?
And if our ultimate goal
is to train something
that can do multiple
tasks at once,
then we can actually
amortize the complexity
of learning any one
task by actually
training that policy across
tasks and across scenarios.
So it could actually be a boost
for data efficiency in the sense
that the data efficiency
for training any one task
will be lower when
you're actually trying
to train everything together.
And that's because
tasks typically
will have some sort
of shared structure,
if you're trying to be a
language model assistant,
there is going to be a shared
structure with regard to grammar
or maybe with regard
to different websites.
And if you learn how to
interact with one website,
that can teach you something
about how to interact
with other websites.
Or with legged
robots, if your goal
is to be able to walk
forward and walk backward,
then this shared notion
of staying balanced
will be shared across
tasks, among other things.
Or if you're trying to develop
a recommender system that's
personalized to different
users, then some users
will share a lot
of similarities,
where if you try to learn to
be a great recommender for one
person, then there are other
people that you could also
probably be a recommender for.
And then there's also a slightly
deeper motivation as well,
which is that when
we actually try
to change these general systems
rather than systems that
do one task, we often find
that generalist systems end up
being more reliable and
more performant than if we
were to just train on one task.
And so I think that this is
a pretty cool finding that
has empirically been true
in recent years in AI.
And so it's extra motivation
for not just training
something for one particular
task or problem or user.
Let's maybe get into what
this actually entails.
And we actually
need to think about,
how do we think
about what a task is?
It's actually, in some
ways, not very well defined,
what makes something a
different task versus not
a different task.
But one way to think about it
is having different tasks just
be different RL problems,
different Markov decision
processes.
And so each task will have
a state space, action space,
an initial state distribution,
a transition model, and a reward
function.
And I'm indexing
these with index i
to denote that this is the
state space for task i.
This is the action
space for task i,
the dynamics and reward
for task i, and so forth.
Now, with this
definition, it's worth
mentioning that when we think
of the notion of a task,
there's a meaning under
the English word of task.
And this notion of
a task being an MDP
is actually potentially
quite different
from that semantic
notion of a task,
where you could actually
have different tasks that
have potentially the
same reward function
and only have
different dynamics.
For example, if you're
trying to walk forward
on grass versus trying to
walk forward on flat terrain,
then that potentially could be
considered two different tasks
under this framework,
even though they're both
the task of walking forward.
OK, so a few examples of
multitask problems that we might
think about.
One is this personalized
recommendation problem
that I mentioned.
In this case, different tasks
would be different users
or different people.
And different people might have
different reward functions.
Like, if it's a
music recommendation,
someone might really
love rock music.
Another person really
might love hip-hop music.
And also, the dynamics with
regard to how often they even
listen to music and so forth
might also change across users.
Reinforcement learning-- this is
an application we haven't really
talked about, but it's often
used in character animation
in order to actually
create animations
of different kinds
of characters,
like people or other
animated characters that
appear in movies.
And you might want
to allow and be
able to animate a character to
do lots of different maneuvers.
So you might want to be able
to have your character be
able to do a backflip
or to be able to run
or be able to do a cartwheel.
And each of these would
be different tasks.
Does anyone have
thoughts for these tasks?
What is the thing that
would vary across tasks
versus be fixed across tasks?
Yeah.
So in this scenario, the reward
will vary because in one case,
you want it to run.
In another case, you want
it to do a cartwheel.
And the dynamics or the
physics of the simulator
will stay the same.
Cool.
There's also been
works that's trying
to do character animation
involving different garments,
so like a character that can put
on a shirt versus a long sleeve
shirt versus a dress.
Does anyone have
thoughts on what
would vary across these tasks?
Yeah.
So the policy might vary.
The policy will
also vary, actually,
in all of these cases
for different tasks.
Yeah.
So the physics of how
a long-sleeve shirt
versus a short-sleeve shirt will
behave will vary across tasks.
I think I also put the initial
state distribution might also
vary, whereas in
the first example,
maybe the initial
state is always
to, say, start standing
up, for example,
whereas here, you have different
garments in the initial state.
And then the last
example I put is, maybe
different tasks are controlling
different robot arms.
And maybe one robot arm
looks like this with maybe 4
degrees of freedom.
This one has 6
This one has 7
degrees of freedom.
Does anyone have
thoughts on what
would vary across
tasks if one task is
to control the first
robot to grasp an object,
the second task is to control
the second robot to grasp
an object, and so forth?
Yeah.
So the actions themselves--
so you'll have different
dimensions of actions.
Yeah.
So the dynamics will
also be different.
Because when you
move one joint, that
will affect the other
joints differently.
Yeah.
So the states would
also vary as well.
So how you represent
the arm, that
will be a different dimension.
What the actions even are will
also be different dimensional.
And then the dynamics will
also vary quite a bit as well
because how your
actions affect the robot
arm are going to change.
Cool.
So those are examples
of different problems
where we might want to be
training different tasks.
The last thing that
we're missing here
is, we need to figure
out how to identify
one task from another
task so that we
can tell our policy
what task it should
be doing at a given point.
And one way to do this is
to just assign an index.
You could say this
robot is task 0.
This robot is task 1.
This robot is task
2 and so forth.
If you don't have any other
better way to identify a task,
this is kind of
what you resort to.
You could also have a language
description of the task.
You could have a
video illustration
of what the task is.
There's actually
a number of ways
to be creative with how you
describe the task to the policy.
And we'll refer to each of these
as different task identifiers.
So the task identifier
for the task of--
well, actually, we'll see some
examples on the next slide.
Now, once you have
the task identifier,
an alternative view on
the multitask RL problem
is simply just having
the task identifier
be part of the state,
where we're writing
s bar as the original state.
And what this means
is that before,
we had a kind of a
collection of MDPs.
That's what's
written at the top.
And we can construct a
single MDP that actually
covers all of the tasks.
We have, for example, the
Pi of the initial state,
Pi of s prime, given
s, a and ri of s, a.
And this is like the dynamics
and the reward for each task.
And we can think of
it as like, our goal
is to solve all of the
MDPs for each of the tasks.
But we can also think about
it as just a single MDP, where
the state is now defined
as like, maybe this
is the original state
space of these tasks.
And the state is now defined
as the original state
space and the task
identifier for that task.
And then the reward
function, for example,
in this modified MDP--
that's just a single
MDP for all the tasks--
is then going to be equal to--
let's say, just to be explicit,
the reward for this
state and this action
would then be equal
to ri of s bar a.
And similarly, you can write
something out for the dynamics
as well, where the aggregate
MDP for a given task,
s prime given s bar zi comma a
is equal to the kind of dynamics
for that task.
This gets a little
bit more complicated
if your tasks have different
state spaces and action spaces.
And so if they
have, for example,
different
dimensionalities, then you
need to think about how you
would represent this state
space in the MDP.
If they have the same state
space and action space,
you can basically construct
this aggregated Markov decision
process with these
equations here.
Now, if we go back to what we
think of as the single task
reinforcement learning setting
that we've talked about so far,
we can then think
about multitask RL
but where the task identifier
is part of the state, where
the task identifier
could be the task,
like an index, a
language description.
It could also be some
desired goal state
as well that you want to reach.
This is often referred to
as goal-conditioned RL.
But then once you
do this, you're
basically getting a modified MDP
that covers each of these tasks.
Now, in terms of the
reward, like we talked about
on the board, it's basically
going to be the same as before.
In this special case of
goal-conditioned reinforcement
learning, where you're trying to
reach a goal, then oftentimes,
you'll think about the reward
as some negative distance
between the state that you're
currently at and the goal state.
And distance functions
can be Euclidean.
It could be a sparse
0, 1 and so forth.
So we still get kind of a
standard Markov decision process
when we bring these
tasks together.
And you might ask, if we can get
this standard Markov decision
process that now has a task
identifier, like a task string,
as part of the state
space, then why not
apply standard reinforcement
learning algorithms to them?
And the answer is, you can.
And in many cases,
this is a great way
to approach scenarios where you
want to learn multiple tasks.
But the reason why I'm
bringing all this up
is that in some cases,
you can actually
do better by leveraging
the known structure
between different tasks.
And goal-conditioned RL
is one of those cases
where you're trying to
reach different goals.
And in the next
few slides, we'll
talk about one
particular way that you
can do a lot better by
leveraging this fact
that this MDP consists
of these different tasks
that you're trying to do.
Yeah.
Euclidean L2, that's
just mean squared error.
Yeah.
So the question is, if different
people are different tasks,
then is there a better way
to represent different people
than a one hot--
when I say one hot, by the
way, I mean a vector like this
where, if you're going to
represent the number 2,
you use a one-hot vector.
So yeah, there are definitely
better ways than just this.
This is actually fairly common
in a lot of reinforcement
learning methods.
For example, one
thing you could do
is, you could try
to get a language
description of the person
or their preferences.
You could also--
this gets into stuff
that we'll talk about next week.
But you could also use
some examples of things
that they like and don't like
as part of the task descriptor
as well.
And so you get something
more like in-context learning
in that case, where zi actually
might contain some data
about the task.
So yeah, there are some
better examples like that.
So in terms of
this problem setup,
let's actually
look at an example.
So we can just start with
multitask imitation learning.
And in the multitask
imitation learning
setting, we can think of it as,
if we have different tasks, i,
if the number of tasks, i, is
a relatively small number, then
you can basically
think of it as having
some set of demonstrations that
are demonstration trajectories
for each task,
where each of these
contains expert demonstrations.
So these are demos for task i.
And this is for i equals 1 to N
if you have N different tasks.
And if we were to
think about how
to use this data for
imitation learning,
thinking back to
the second lecture,
we were doing
imitation learning.
We had this objective of
minimizing the log probability
of actions' given states.
And if we just write this as
minimizing the supervised loss
function with respect to
our policy parameters,
then when we want to move to
the multitask setting, what
we can do is, we can simply try
to now minimize a single policy
set of policy parameters over
the loss function averaged
over all of the tasks.
So this is basically like
multitask imitation learning,
pretty simple, hopefully.
One useful trick for
this sort of approach
is that if tasks are very
different, like if one task is
telling you to go
forward, one task is
telling you to go backwards--
maybe one task is
telling you to lie down.
They're telling the policy
to do very different things.
Then if you sampled one
mini batch that's mostly
going forward and a different
mini batch of mostly laying
down, for example, then from
one gradient step to the next,
you're actually going to
have a lot of variance.
Because the first
mini batch is going
to tell you to do
something that's
pretty different from
the second mini batch.
And hopefully, the
policy should be
able to use the task identifier
to differentiate the two.
But in some cases, it
can be a little bit
tricky for the
network to do that.
And so one thing
that's quite useful
is that when you
sample a mini batch,
you can stratify the
mini batch and ensure
that each mini batch of data
has data from each task.
And if you're trying to optimize
for uniform distribution
over your tasks, then your
mini batch would be like--
1/n of the data would
be the first task.
1/n of the mini batch would be
the second task and so forth.
And this will give you gradients
that are lower variance.
And it can be quite
useful in practice
to do something like this.
Another thing that I didn't
put on the slides that can also
be useful is making sure that
your states and actions are
on similar scales across tasks.
So per-task
normalization can also
be quite useful for
the learning process.
Now, we've talked about
training this multitask policy.
And when we do that,
we're now going
to have a policy that takes as
input some state and some task
descriptor and then needs
to output some action.
And you might have
scenarios where
this is like a language
string or a one-hot vector
and this is an image.
And that's inherently a
very multimodal problem.
You have different
data modalities.
These are very
different dimensions.
And so in practice,
there's a question of,
how do you design
architectures that
take as input this kind
of multimodal data?
One example that I'll give
that I like because it actually
uses multiple different
modalities of task descriptors
is this paper here, where
the goal is a multitask
imitation learning system,
is training a robot
to do some simple
manipulation tasks.
And the way the
architecture works--
this paper is a little bit old,
so it's not using a transformer.
But here's the current
state right here.
It actually
downsamples the image
before passing it
into the model.
And then it also uses, actually,
two different task descriptors.
So it uses a language string as
one task descriptor, which is
put bottle in the ceramic bowl.
And it also trains
the model to be
able to, instead of
using the language,
be able to use a video
of how to do the task.
In this case, the
video is a video
of a person placing
the bottle in the bowl.
And so you can design models
that in this case then,
for the language, use a language
encoder, like things that
are typically used in
language models, for example,
transformers.
And actually, I think
the language encoder here
did actually use a transformer.
And then, separately,
for the video,
it would be using a
different kind of encoder
because video data
looks very different.
And it uses a video encoder
for the second part.
And then it kind of
multiplies these embeddings
into different layers
of the network,
the backbone of the network
that processes the state.
And then the loss
function corresponds
to a behavior-cloning loss.
And it either samples
the task descriptor
from the video encoder or
from the language encoder.
And then the whole model,
including these encoders,
is trained using the
behavior-cloning loss.
So this is one
practical example.
Now, we can also look at some
more modern architectures.
And first off, if
you have something
like a language model,
the task descriptor,
it's very natural for it
just to be a language string.
And you can think of that
basically just as the prompt.
And so one way to think about
multitask imitation learning is,
basically, all of the language
model imitation learning
or supervised fine-tuning
is with different prompts.
You can sort of think of
those as different tasks.
And it's very easy to just
pass that into a transformer.
And in terms of modern
policy architectures
for using task
strings in robotics,
it's often common to
also use a transformer
and find ways to
use image encoders,
in this case, pre-trained
image encoders, project
those into the input
space of a language model,
also use the task
descriptor here,
which is, what should
the robot do to put
the eggplant in the bowl?
Pass those in as tokens
to a language model.
And then output the actions
and train the whole model,
including the image encoder and
the text encoder end to end.
So here, you can view
the task identifier zi
as basically the
prompt for the model.
The question is, how
does this compare
to traditional
reinforcement learning
in terms of task performance
and success rate?
So I guess there's a couple of
things that are different here.
We'll talk about multitask RL
in a bit, right after this.
And then so you can do this sort
of prompt conditioning, task
identifier conditioning
both with imitation learning
and with reinforcement learning.
And generally,
the considerations
about imitation
learning versus RL
is very similar to what
we've discussed so far, where
with imitation
learning, you're not
able to use a reward function
to improve over the expert data.
But it's very simple
and it's very easy
to scale simple things
to large data sets,
whereas RL has a lot of
potential and can help a lot
when you have some
reward information
and you want to
optimize those rewards.
And you can actually
do a lot better
than some provided data set.
And then just some
examples of what
multitask imitation learning
policies might look like--
the examples from those
two prior architectures--
the robots are doing
very simple things.
And so I wanted
to pick something
that's a bit more recent.
So here, the task identifier
is in the top left.
In this video, there'll
just be two tasks.
One is to flatten the towel,
and one is to hang the towel.
And so for the first part, the
task is to flatten the towel.
And then here, we're
actually stringing together
multiple tasks.
So at the point where the robot
is at a point where the towel is
in a more flattened state, the
human actually switches the task
and then tells the robot, now
I want you to hang the towel.
And this, again, is passed into
a transformer for the robot
to do that task.
So this is a case where
there's two tasks.
You can also do, actually, a
lot more tasks, potentially.
So here's an example where
there's I think more than 10
tasks, 10 different
language strings
that the robot follows, so like,
put the plate in the drawer.
Close the microwave.
Drive the base backward.
Rotate the base left.
And one of the things that's
interesting to note here
is that tasks can also have
different levels of abstraction.
So you might have a
level of abstraction
of just like, drive forward or
move your right gripper lower.
Or you might have
something that's
much higher, like
throw the napkin away
or something like that.
The question is, if you had
one policy for each task,
would that run similar
to this or different?
Yeah.
So in this case, it's one
policy with the prompt as input.
You could also have a different
policy, one for each task.
If you don't do any--
what I would call weight
sharing, like if you have,
basically, completely
different set
of parameters for
every single task,
then you can't
really make use of--
the weights are only trained
on data from that one task.
And you're going to
have a smaller data set.
And so usually,
in many scenarios
that performs worse than
training a single policy.
Another consideration is that it
ends up using a lot more memory
to store all those weights.
And you might actually need to
reload the model into memory.
And so it can take longer to
switch between different tasks.
But sometimes there are
also optimization challenges
with trying to fit multiple
tasks into one model.
And so sometimes there
are some circumstances
where training different
policies for different tasks
can be useful.
Yeah.
So the question is, are
these systems hierarchical?
Like, some of these tasks
are fairly high level.
So the next part
of this slide is,
what about even more
high-level tasks?
Like, what if you wanted to tell
the robot, clean the kitchen?
For the videos that
I've shown here,
this is just one single
policy that's doing it.
But hierarchy is very useful
for higher-level tasks.
And if you just told this
robot to clean the kitchen,
it wouldn't be able to do
what it did in this video.
And so we'll have a lecture
on hierarchy in, I think,
two-ish weeks.
And we'll talk about
exactly that and scenarios
where we could try to do
even higher-level tasks.
But yeah, even with a single
policy, a single flat policy
without hierarchy, it is able to
do reasonable actions for tasks
that are somewhat high level.
What does long-horizon
task mean?
By that, I mean a task that
takes a long time, basically,
where you takes many time steps.
You have to take a lot
of different actions
in order to do that.
And there's generally
a number of challenges
that can come up with
long-horizon tasks, such
as you have to be thinking
about what you should be doing
in order to complete that.
And there's lots of things
you could do to complete that.
So there might be multimodality.
In reinforcement
learning settings,
you might also have
sparse rewards.
And you might not get reward
feedback for a very long time.
Yeah.
So the question is, a lot of
these tasks are pretty similar.
What if you wanted a task
that's more vision based--
I think you said.
Yeah.
So this particular
model was actually
also trained to do
certain vision tasks,
like asking questions
about the image
and captioning an image,
that sort of stuff.
And if you have a
big enough model,
it's not too hard to do that.
But generally, you
do need larger models
to be able to do more things.
Cool.
So we've talked a bit about
multi-task imitation learning.
Now what about multitask RL?
Basically, the story
is pretty similar.
We can feed as input a task
descriptor into the policy,
feed as input a task descriptor
into a Q function or a value
function.
Whatever we're
learning, we can pass
in that prompt or some
other descriptor of the task
into the models.
If you have a discrete
number of tasks,
then it can be useful to
have a different replay
buffer for each task,
especially if you
want to try to balance the
sampling of each batch.
And now there's this
question of sharing data.
And this comes up specifically
in reinforcement learning,
not in imitation learning.
So in particular,
if we collected
some sort of exploratory
data for a task when-- like,
maybe our policy was told
to pick up the sponge
or something like that.
Our policy did something.
It might not have
picked up the sponge
because it might
have made a mistake.
That sort of experience might
be useful for other task
descriptors as well.
And if we have a per-task replay
buffer, like one for each task,
then we're not
actually going to be
updating the policy for
other tasks using that data.
And we could actually
think about scenarios
where we might actually be able
to reuse data from one task
to actually more explicitly
help the model or the policy
learn something
about another task.
And if we were to
do this, we actually
have to relabel the data.
So specifically, if the tasks
have different reward functions
but maybe the same
dynamics, then you'd
have to actually
change the reward
label in the data set
for it to be the reward
label for the other task.
So let's walk
through an example.
So say that you are trying
to learn to play hockey.
And there's maybe some
teammates in blue.
There is a goalkeeper from
the other team in orange.
And maybe one task is passing.
Another task is shooting a goal.
And maybe you are trying to
shoot a goal, but you messed up
and you accidentally actually
making a pretty good pass
to your teammate.
Then that data that you just
collected, even though you
were intending to shoot a goal,
that data actually is probably
pretty useful for learning
how to be better at passing.
And so what you could
do is, you could
store that experience as
normal under the original task
identifier.
But you could also relabel
the experience with task
with the task 1
ID, specifically,
the passing ID--
there's a typo there--
and then store that in the
replay buffer for that task.
And so specifically what this
algorithm would look like is--
maybe you pick
one of your tasks.
And then we pick a
corresponding task identifier.
Then we're going
to collect data.
And we'll be collecting
data from our policy.
That's going to be
then conditioned
on that task identifier.
And maybe let's refer
to this data as--
it'll have st,
at, st plus 1, rt.
And then it will also
have the task identifier.
We'll maybe put this into
a replay buffer for task i.
So we'll store this
in the replay buffer.
And then we could actually
then potentially use
this for another task as well.
So that's what I'm
calling relabeling.
And we could consider this
data-- so st, at, st plus 1.
But we could actually consider
it for a different task, maybe
task j.
And so the reward
for task j would
be r of j for st, at and the
task identifier for task j.
And we could take this
data that's been relabeled
and add this to either
our shared replay
buffer or our replay
buffer for task j.
And so then we're actually
using experience for one task
to learn another task.
And then we might do
this for multiple tasks.
Eventually, we will update
our policy, pi theta,
and collect some more data.
Yeah.
So the question is, how do we
decide if it's worth relabeling?
And in particular, if we're
doing this for task j,
which task j should we pick?
Should we do it for all j's?
Should we only do
it for some j's?
this some of the time?
This ends up being somewhat
kind of a heuristic process.
Because it's a little bit
hard to tell, generally,
if data will be useful
for learning one task
or not because
learning is somewhat
of an amorphous process.
The one heuristic is
that if our j was high,
then it might be good
for learning that task.
Because you actually might have
accidentally done something good
for a different task.
So that's one heuristic.
Another heuristic sometimes is
just to also sample randomly
and use it for all tasks
at random and uniformly.
How does this work
for continuous state?
There's nothing here that
assumes discrete states.
How do you reach--
so what I've written here is
like a relabeling algorithm
for any sort of
multitask system.
We'll talk about what this looks
like for goal-condition settings
in a minute if that's what
you're wondering about.
Yeah.
So this is a great point.
You can't do this universally.
And so this is something
that's called hindsight
relabeling because you
look at what you did.
If you did something
good, then in hindsight,
you can then relabel that
to be a different task.
So in terms of this
algorithm on the slides,
we collect some data
using some policy.
We store that data
in a replay buffer.
We are going to perform
hindsight relabeling.
And what this looks
like is, we originally
collected it for task i.
We're going to relabel it
with the reward for task j.
And then we'll store
that relabeled data
in a replay buffer.
The slides have this for a
single combined replay buffer.
You could also do this with
different replay buffers
for each task.
Then you'll update your
policy with the replay buffer
and repeat this process.
In terms of which
tasks to choose,
you can choose this randomly,
task to get high rewards.
The note here is
also, you can actually
do it for trajectories
that get high rewards,
not just transitions
that get high rewards.
Because if there's a high reward
somewhere in the trajectory,
then other parts
of the trajectory
might have done
something good as well.
Yeah.
And then there's a question of,
when can we apply relabeling?
And in particular,
there's actually
restrictions on both the
set of MDPs or the MDPs
of the different tasks
and also on the algorithm
that you're using for
reinforcement learning.
So does anyone have
thoughts on what
has to be shared or not
shared for this algorithm
to make sense?
Yeah, so a shared
state action space.
So you're going to want a
shared state and action space.
Anything else do you want
that's shared and not shared?
Yeah.
So if you only have
one replay buffer,
then you want the dimensions
of your state and actions
to match and, generally, for
the state space and action
space to be the same.
Yeah.
So you probably want the
initial state distribution
to be similar.
So you want p of s1 to be
similar for different tasks.
Because if it's drastically
different, then probably,
sharing data won't be as useful.
So if one of them has dense
rewards and one of them
has sparse rewards,
that might be a problem.
That is true.
Although, that might be a
problem generally in multitask
RL.
But actually, in
this case, I don't
think it's going
to be especially
an issue in this case.
Because you are going
to be using the reward
function for the task.
But yeah, generally,
for multitask RL,
that makes things challenging.
Yeah.
So it's helpful for the
rewards to be the same scale.
What about the dynamics?
Should they be the same
or different across tasks?
Same, yeah.
So you want the
dynamics to be the same.
And that's actually
really important.
Because you're not
relabeling the dynamics here.
And because you're not
relabeling the dynamics
if they're different
across tasks, then yeah,
it's going to be a problem.
And so this is only
applicable-- because you're
teaching the model and
sharing data with the dynamics
from the other task, it's really
important for the dynamics
to be the same.
So the dynamics
should be the same.
And then this is also most
useful if the reward functions
are different.
Otherwise, the data is
already in the buffer
with the original
reward function.
My last question is, do you
need this to be an off-policy RL
algorithm, or is it OK
if this is on policy?
Any thoughts on that?
We'd like to have cover.
So off policy is generally good.
Yeah.
So the action here--
this was the action that
was taken by the policy
when conditioned on zi.
And when conditioned
on zj, the policy
might have done
something different.
And so this data
that we're relabeling
is going to be off-policy data.
And so that means that when
we're updating pi theta,
we really need to be using
an off-policy algorithm
because this data is not
following the policy conditioned
on zj.
Yeah, exactly.
So if you're going to be
using importance weights,
you need to store
which policy collected
the data in the first place.
Well, actually, sorry.
Let me think about that.
This data is actually changed
from the original data.
And so actually, for
the importance weights,
you'll actually want to use
zj, not zi, as the old policy.
Because you're actually kind
of creating synthetic data
that is as if you were using zj.
So yeah.
Sorry, I misspoke.
So you don't need to store
which policy it came from.
OK.
Oh.
The other thing is, you need
the reward function form here.
You need to actually compute
the rewards for the new task.
That's also important as well.
Or you need to have learned
the reward function.
So you need the reward function.
The dynamics has
to be consistent.
And you have to be using
an off-policy algorithm.
And then lastly is the
goal-conditioned version.
This is basically
the same as before,
but our reward function is
now this negative distance
between states.
And for continuous
states, this could
be like mean squared error.
It could be a distance
in embedding space.
Or it could be a 0, 1
loss within some epsilon
ball of the goal state.